Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. Today's דף Daf is קח. Kuf
Chet. Welcome. We are, like I said, every day getting one day
closer to the end. Alright, forty-seven days in the כתובות, Ketubot, I
guess. Anyway, no. So we take at the משנה Mishna at the
bottom of ק"ז עמוד ב Kuf Zayin Amud Bet and we are
dealing again, remember, with the interesting rulings of חנן Chanan and who
was the other one and אדמון, Admon, and we have one of
חנן Chanan about whether you when a person has gone overseas and
his wife is supported by the estate, rejecting שמואל's Shmuel non-פשט pshat
read of that, that we would support his wife from the estate
when he's overseas. Do you make her שבועה shevua only at the
end or at the beginning and the end, and אדמון Admon said
only and חנן Chanan said only at the end. So the second
ruling of חנן Chanan also relates to the same scenario. Let's take
a look. Bottom of ק"ז עמוד ב. Kuf Zayin Amud Bet. מי
שהלך למדינת הים, Mi she-halach limdinat hayam,
somebody went overseas, ועמד אחד ופרנס את אשתו, ve-amad echad ve-pirnes et
ishto,
and somebody said, 'Look נעבעך, nebach, his wife, he, this guy didn't
leave any food for his wife.' Same concern. So rather than what
we learned in the previous משנה Mishna that the wife can go
to בית דין Beit Din and you know according to חנן Chanan
only you'd have to take her שבועה shevua at the end of
the whole process, somebody had רחמנות rachmanut and just said, 'You know
what? I'm just going to send her over some food.' Okay? Some
storekeeper or some nice people in the community and they basically provided
her with food for the entire time that he was away. And
then the guy returned. So can the guy now say, 'You know,
I took care of your marital responsibilities there. Pay me back for
all the money that I spent.' So חנן אומר Chanan omer איבד
את מעותיו. ibed et maotav. He flushed his money down the toilet.
Okay. So
you know, that was very nice of him to do it, very
nice of you to, you know, to take care of my responsibilities
for me, but you never asked, we never made any contractual arrangement,
I never borrowed any money from you, so I don't owe you
anything.
Might you still have paid for the some values, what he would
have had to pay for? In other words, she consumes a dollar
a day, whatever.
Okay, so let's say so let's say you come along and you
feed my dog, right? Does that create a of the objective reality
that my dog ate, you know, was sustained by your food, does
that create a debt? So that's part of what we're going to
discuss, that's part of what this huge תוספות Tosfot is about. But
חנן Chanan says no. You know, it was very nice for you
to do it, but there's no thing lasting of what you of
what you did and I don't owe you any money. נחלקו עליו
בני כהנים גדולים. Nechlaku alav Bnei Kohanim Gedolim. So again these בני
כהנים גדולים Bnei Kohanim Gedolim are yet with them like they did
last time. ואמרו ישבע כמה הוציא
ויטול. Ve-amru yishava kama hotzi ve-yitol. בני כהנים גדולים Bnei Kohanim Gedolim
are big into שבועה. shevua. So they say take a שבועה, shevua,
you have to so we have to know how much you spent,
but you're entitled to be reimbursed. אמר רבי דוסא בן הרכינס Amar
Rabbi Dosa ben Harkinas מכדבריהם. mikidvreihem. רבי דוסא בן הרכינס Rabbi Dosa
ben Harkinas follows them, the sides line up exactly like they did
in the previous משנה, Mishna, right? רבי דוסא בן הרכינס Rabbi Dosa
ben Harkinas sides with the בני כהנים גדולים, Bnei Kohanim Gedolim, and
אמר רבי יוחנן בן זכאי, amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, רבי יוחנן
בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai who in the last משנה Mishna
sided with חנן, Chanan, sides with חנן Chanan here as well. יפה
אמר חנן. Yafeh amar Chanan. חנן Chanan said correctly. הניח מעותיו על
קרן הצבי. Hinniach meotav al keren hatzvi. It's like you put your
money on the horns of a deer. Okay? Of like that would
have been their idiom for it's like you flush your money down
the toilet. Alright, so you know, you threw your money away. It's
not my responsibility. Okay. So, so what is going on here? So,
you know, Michael asks the question, I guess I'll just reference it
briefly because there's this huge תוספות Tosfot which makes our דף daf
a lot shorter. Michael asks the question, which is, 'Okay, maybe you
didn't borrow any money, and maybe I didn't hire you, but is
there some times when I objectively do you a favor that that
creates a debt to from you to me?' And there are two
scenarios about this. One is, you know, you're away and your lawn
is looking terrible and I go ahead and I mow your lawn.
Okay? Or that's a contemporary suburban example. Or in the case of
the גמרא, Gemara, you know, you're letting your field lay fallow and
who knows where you are, you're absentee, and I say, 'This is
such a waste,' and I go ahead and I plant your field
for you. Okay. So can I go ahead and demand at least
like the normal fee of a of a laborer? Right? Now if
everybody could do that, then like why do I have to go
around soliciting business for my lawn mowing business? I'll just go. So
okay, so maybe maybe I can't always exact like the exact like
the best fee for it or whatever, but is there a reality
that there might be an implicit hiring that goes on there? And
that has to do with like is it a שדה העשויה ליטע,
sadei ha-asuya lita, לא עשויה ליטע, lo asuya lita, like is there
a presumption that of course you would want somebody to do it?
So even without explicitly contracting, we could say somehow that objectively creates
almost like a, you know, a hired a you know a contractual
relationship because clearly you would want to do it. But even in
the cases where it's not clearly it's not שדה העשויה ליטע, sadei
ha-asuya lita, is there just a reality that your property has improved
and since your property has improved, so you know, you have something
you have some benefit in increased value in the
property. The difference is is that like if you are, you know,
fattening my cows, so then I have fatter cows, maybe I owe
you some money. But you're feeding my wife, okay, and it's not
like my property value has gone up as a result. I don't
have any actual increased value that I have that now demands that
I somehow pay you back. It's like you gave me something. Conceptually,
the way we normally explain that is if your, I don't know,
football rolled into my yard, I have your football in my yard.
I gotta give it to you. If you happen to have, you
know, increased my property value, it's almost in an abstract way like
your property, your
effort, your manure, your whatever has now increased the value of my
yard. I have something of yours there. I've got to pay you
back for it. Okay, but here there's no increased property value that
I have. So here, you know, that's why תוספות Tosafot says that
you're able to say here what I really just did is I,
you know, discharged an obligation of yours, but I didn't actually, it
didn't actually result in any increased value that you have, so that's
why it's possible to say that I don't owe you anything. Now,
it still sounds very strange, but again, that's how we sort of
try to navigate these issues. תוספות Tosafot compares it to a similar
discussion in the גמרא Gemara about מבריח ארי מנכסי חברו. Mavriach Ari
Mi-nichsei Chaveiro. Let's say I see a lion coming and it's about
to attack your sheep. Like the story about, was that
by שמשון, Shimshon, right, with the lion and then he tore open
its mouth or whatever, fine. Okay, I see a lion that's about
to attack your sheep and I go ahead and I hire some
shepherds in the town and we all come with our sticks and
our torches and we scare away the lion and I shelled out
$100 and I saved your sheep. And you say, 'Okay, thank you
very much. I don't have any increased property value here. I don't
owe you anything.' So no, the גמרא Gemara is clear that I
do have to reimburse you for your expenses, for your efforts. So
תוספות Tosafot says like why is this any different, right? Because I,
you know, here's a creditor essentially, the woman basically, you know, would
have taken your property to pay off the debt. I basically, you
know, stopped her from doing that by providing her the food. So
תוספות Tosafot basically says it could be very much in principle the
case about scaring off the lion, you're also exempt. But as a
matter of public policy, we want to allow, we want to ensure
that people actually do act on behalf of their neighbor and come
to their aid if they're not around. And therefore, we're going to
insist that they be reimbursed. There was no need to institute, thank
you, such a type of a thing for public policy here because
the woman has an option. Her option is that she could go
ahead and, you know, why do we have to stop your wife?
Why would we want a public policy thing to encourage other people
to pay off your debt to your wife? Just let her, just
let her just take your property and why don't you pay off
your debt to your wife? So תוספות, Tosafot, but anyway, so that's
his basic approach. And the bottom line is that, yes, it's a
little bit ironic, but if you stop me from being, if you
help me prevent a creditor from taking my property,
you know, that's what חנן Chanan says. I mean, again, it sounds
like a stupid public policy type of a rule,
but איבד מעותיו, Ibad Me'otav, I didn't wind up with any, you
know, you didn't, I don't have any increased property value due to
you. You just stopped me from being hurt. There's no public policy
reason why we would want to, you know, encourage such behavior. So
I wind up holding the bag and that's what חנן Chanan says.
Yes.
If she, if she could have just as easily taken the fruit
for herself from her husband's property, then how could the other man
say ישבע כמה הוציא ויטול? Yishava Kama Hotzi V'yitol?
Well, so that's an interesting question. Is there some parallel, some, not
parallel, some relationship between this debate and the debate in the previous
משנה? Mishnah? And I, you know, I haven't seen anybody that says
it explicitly, but I wonder if there is and exactly along the
lines you say. חנן Chanan says it's easy for her to take
the property. He says you don't have to take an oath. We'll
just go to בית דין Beit Din and they'll just give you
the property to pay your food bill. So if it's so easy
for her to take the property, so what this guy did was
really completely unnecessary. And if you want to be an astute and,
you know, do this when she has an easy option, you know,
then that's just your own, you know, you're just, you're just wasting
your own money, it's very easy for her. Whereas according to the
בני כהנים גדולים, Bnei Kohanim Gedolim, it's not so easy for her.
There's a whole, you know, she has to take an oath and
maybe there's more roadblocks and it's a more complicated procedure. So there
maybe they want to make it actually maybe more possible for there
to be alternatives. And therefore they say, you know, if somebody else
wants to help her out because now she has to take this
oath, he has this obstacle, and wants to help her out, we'll
see to it that that guy can go ahead and get reimbursed.
So I think there might be a relationship between those debates. Yes.
Would it be the same as if I go and I pay
your employees and I don't have to get paid back?
Interesting, possibly. Yeah. I guess what applies to a lot of this
material is the motivation and the personal relationships involved. A total stranger
is not going to go around and say can I give you
the money that your husband doesn't want to pay. Right. Exactly.
Sure, the town maybe the towns people see her and feel bad
for
her, maybe you're right, there's some obviously relationship which is motivating this,
but that doesn't translate into a personal relationship doesn't translate into a
legal responsibility, right? So if you want to see some of the
key lines of תוספות, Tosafot, that's just חנן אומר איבד מעותיו, Chanan
Omer Ibed Meosav, like תוספות ד"ה להוציא מהא דקיימא לן היורד לתוך
שדה חברו ונטעה שלא ברשות דשיימינן ליה כאריס ולבונה חורבת חברו דנותן
לו מה שהנהנהו.
Tosafot dibur hamatchil lehoxsi meha dekaima lan hayored letoch sdei chavero venataah
shelo birshut deshaminan lei kearis ulevoneh
churvat chavero denoten lo mah shehenahu. התם השבח בעין הוא, Hatam hashevach
baayin hu, ודין הוא שיטול. vedin hu sheyitol. There there's actual physical
increased value. אבל הכא לא השביח לו שום שבח נכסים, Aval hacha
lo hispbiach lo shum shevach nechasim, אלא שהצילו מגביית בעל חוב, ella
shehetzilo migiviyat baal chov, ולא מידי יהיב ליה, velo miyad yahiv lei,
והוי כמבריח ארי מנכסי חברו, vehavei kemavriach ari minechasei chavero, ואף על
גב דמהנהו לא מתחייב. veaf al gav demit'hano lo mitchayev. Okay, fact
is, you benefited me, but I don't have actually physical increase in
value, you just stopped me from being damaged as it were from
my wife seizing my property and I don't know you. And then
if you skip a little bit advance in תוספות, Tosafot,
he says like this, he says, you see right before on the
next page, the where the lines get medium-sized underneath the גמרא, Gemara,
right after, you know, the actual text of the גמרא, Gemara, תוספות
Tosafot says like this, אלא תקנת חכמים ella takanat chachamim
two lines before the lines get wide medium-sized, תקנת חכמים התם שישלמו
לו כדי שישיב אבידתו של חברו וכן בקדם ברועים ובמקלות. takanat chachamim
hatam sheyeshalmu lo kedei sheyashiv aveidato shel chavero vechen bekadam beroyim uvemaklot.
So if you went ahead and, you know, returned some lost objects,
prevented them from getting lost, or you hired some shepherds, בשכר דחוזר
ונוטל שכר מבעל הבית כדי שיעסוק להבריח את הארי. bischar dechozer venotel
sachar mibaal habayit kedei sheyaasok lehavriach et haari. There might be times
when you chase away a lion that we actually, I do pay
you for your efforts, I'm legally obligated because we want to encourage
that type of activity. ואפילו עולה כדי דמיהן נפקא מינה לכושרא דחיותא,
veafilu olat kedei dameihen nafka mina lekushra dechayuta, אבל פורע חובו, aval
poreiah chovo, ואמר אחר ופרנסת אשתו, veamar acher uperneset ishto, למה לנו
לעשות תקנה זו. lamah lanu laasot takanah zu.
Why should we go ahead and try to encourage that behavior? Let
his wife just take his property, right? It's not a lion eating
up my sheet. I owe money do I my? So why should
I try to encourage somebody else to pay off my debt and
then I have have to reimburse him? All right, but anyway it
is interesting, you know, חנן Chanan is a pretty radical statement. איבד
את מעותיו Ibed et meosav and תוספות Tosafot is trying to figure
it out. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about all
this. Yes, Charlie.
Minor point. צבי Zvi is translated by both Corin and Artscroll as
deer. Rabbi Slifkin says it's actually a gazelle, a type of animal
which has horns.
Which has horns? Yes, I was wondering about the horns of a
deer. Okay, fine, very nice. תנן התם, Tnan hatam,
we taught over there in נדרים. Nedarim. המודר הנאה מחברו. Hamudar hanaah
mechaveiro.
Somebody is a vowed against getting any benefit from his friend. Okay,
so Michael went ahead and took a vow that he can't derive
any benefit from me. All right, so now, but I feel bad
for Michael and I want to help him out. What are the
range of activities I'm able to do that would not be considered
benefiting Michael? Any activities? Well we'll take a look. שוקל לו את
שקלו. Shokel lo et shiklo. I can pay his shekel, his half
shekel that has to be paid every year for the קרבנות, korbanot,
I can pay it. Which seems to be like paying a debt.
That's pretty impressive that I'm able to do that, right?
I saved Michael from paying the shekel. Okay, well we'll take a
look. ופורע את חובו. Uforeiah et chovo. This is even a bigger
חידוש. chiddush. Michael owes Charlie a thousand dollars. I can pay I
can pay that off for him. Okay, you know, anybody wants to
think that that's not הנאה, hanaah, you want to come and pay
all my student debts for me? Oh no, that's not real הנאה.
hanaah. Anyway, ומחזיר לו אבידתו, Umachazir lo aveidato, and can return his
lost object. Now returning his lost object is maybe the least of
the חידושים chiddushim because that actually is Michael's object, number one. So
I'm just giving him what's his. And number two is that I
have a מצוה. mitzvah. So fundamentally I'm doing it, I mean, so
that's a question, like on the one hand my intent is not
to benefit Michael, my intent is just to do the מצוה. mitzvah.
And in practice whether actually did he get something of mine, right,
he only got his own object back. So that's maybe the the
easiest to understand.
ובמקום שנוטלים שכר. Uvemakom shenotlim sachar. Now how about in places where
the practice is that if somebody returns your lost object, you pay
him for his efforts, or at least for his שכר בטלה. schar
batalah. Remember we discussed the other time you're not supposed to get
שכר schar for doing a מצוה, mitzvah, but nevertheless while I was
bothering returning Michael's אבידה aveidah I wasn't able to go and work
at my job or something. So if that's the practice, now we've
got a problem. What's the problem? Michael is gonna now pay me
for the time I took to return his אבידה. aveidah. So we
have two possible scenarios. One scenario is not only can Michael not
get הנאה hanaah from me, but I've also taken a vow that
I can't get הנאה hanaah from Michael. So he can't pay me
any money because then I'm getting הנאה hanaah from Michael. Or even
if I didn't take that vow, Michael wants to give me the
money, so I could accept it. But let's say I don't want
to accept it. Let's say I basically say to Michael, you know
what, keep it. He's not allowed to keep it because since he
now Michael owes me money, right, because I returned the אבידה, Aveidah,
he owes me the money, and I say keep, don't, keep the
money, keep it, I'm now giving him something.
I'm giving him—where the גמרא Gemara is, is that
you—no,
no, no, you Michael can't get הנאה Hana'ah from me. I but
even though you can't get הנאה Hana'ah from me, I can pay
your שקל, Shekel, okay, I can pay off your debt. That's not
considered getting הנאה Hana'ah from me. I can return your אבידה. Aveidah.
But now you want to pay me, and I want to say
to you, you know what, forget it. You don't have to pay
me. Okay, but if I say you don't have to pay me,
he's getting הנאה Hana'ah from me, because I've just essentially, you know,
been מוחל Mochel a debt that he has to me. He owed
me 10 bucks and I say keep it. So what do you
do? So the answer is in that case,
תטיל הנאה להקדש, Tatil Hana'ah Le'hekdesh, give the money to הקדש. Hekdesh.
So you're not getting הנאה Hana'ah from me, I'm not getting הנאה
Hana'ah from you, in that case, in terms of the money, I
don't want to take your 10 dollars, but you can't keep your
10 dollars because—so what do you have to do, you give it
to הקדש. Hekdesh. So that's the old
example—that's the first example which, you know, which is like, do I
owe you 5 dollars? I don't know. I don't remember. You know
what, just give it to צדקה. Tzedakah. Okay, fine. So that's the
variation of—it's like—the whole tradition, I can't take the money, you can't
give the money, alright, give it to הקדש. Hekdesh. Anyway, so we
want to understand these. So the מחזיר אבידה Machzir Aveidah is the
easiest case and it's not directly relevant to us. We're going to
deal with the first two. בשלמא שוקלו את שקלו, Bishlama Shoklo Et
Shiklo, we understand why I can pay off Michael's שקל Shekel even
though he can't get any benefit from it. מצוה קעביד, Mitzvah Ka'avid,
I'm just doing the מצוה. Mitzvah. דתנן Detnan and we taught in
the משנה: Mishnah: תורמין על האבוד, Tormin Al Ha'avud, you can—when they
take the תרומת, Terumat, you know, the money from the collect- שקלים
Shekalim and you use that money to buy the קרבנות. Korbanot. Okay.
What about people that have not yet paid off their שקל? Shekel?
Are the קרבנות Korbanot still being brought for them? Right, every- the
קרבן Korban is supposed to be brought for the whole ציבור. Tzibur.
But we have to start buying them and, you know, there's some
people that pay taxes on time and some people that pay them
very late. And we have to start buying those קרבנות Korbanot before
everybody has paid up. Is the purchases that we're making from or
the—when we take from those collect- שקלים, Shekalim, we know, we do
a תרומה, Terumah, we come in with our baskets and we like
fill them with the שקלים Shekalim and then we go and we,
you know, use it to buy the קרבנות. Korbanot. For whom is
that תרומה Terumah being taken? For whom are the קרבנות Korbanot being
brought? So, על האבוד, Al Ha'avud, even money that was lost. Now,
I'm going to first read it רש"י's Rashi way. רש"י Rashi reads
what that means is, so I basically set my שקל Shekel to
go to the—to be brought to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and
the שליח Shaliach lost it along the way. Or, על הגבוי, Al
Hagavui, or that the—I gave my money to the, you know, to
the officer from the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, I gave him my
שקל Shekel and he has yet to actually bring it to the
בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Okay, which is less of a חידוש Chiddush
than if he actually lost it. ועל העתיד לגבות, Ve'al Ha'atid Ligbot,
or even if I have not even paid the money yet. Okay,
I haven't even sent in my taxes yet, I filed for an
extension or whatever. Since I'm planning on eventually paying, any money that's
used right now to buy the קרבנות Korbanot is being brought on
behalf of—of everybody, even if you haven't basically paid up your money
yet. Okay, now, ועל העתיד לגבות, Ve'al Ha'atid Ligbot, now what does
that have to do with the fact that I can pay off
Michael's שקל? Shekel? So רש"י Rashi says that, look, he says, the
fact that it says על העתיד לגבות Al Ha'atid Ligbot means, let's
say Michael—we'll just use him as an example—has not yet paid his
שקל. Shekel. The קרבנות Korbanot that are being brought even before he
pays his שקל Shekel are still being brought on his behalf. That's
עתיד לגבות, Atid Ligbot, eventually he's going to pay. But then רש"י
Rashi takes it one step further. Since it's brought on the behalf
of somebody who in the future will pay, it's even being brought
on his behalf even if he never winds up paying. Okay, which
is—so basically, this is then a shorthand of basically saying that the
קרבנות Korbanot are being brought for everybody even those that aren't paying.
All right. Now, if that's true, then the paying of the half-שקל
Shekel is not a real, you know, there's not a real consequence
to it, right? Michael's going to get the קרבנות Korbanot brought on
his behalf anyway. It's just a מצוה Mitzvah to give the half-שקל.
Shekel. Just a מצוה Mitzvah to give the half-שקל. Shekel. I did
a מצוה Mitzvah for him. Doing the מצוה Mitzvah isn't הנאה, Hana'ah,
isn't real benefit, you know, מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו. Mitzvot Lav Le'hanot
Nitnu. Real benefit is he got some monetary benefit from me. Either
I relieved him of his debt of the half-שקל Shekel or the
קרבנות Korbanot are now seen as—he's a part-owner in the קרבן. Korban.
But if all that wasn't going to be true anyway, it was
just a question of a מצוה Mitzvah obligation that I got him
out of, big deal, I didn't do anything. Now, that's interesting because
number one, even if it is just a מצוה Mitzvah obligation, does
it really mean that בית דין Beit Din would not come along
and, had I not paid it, still send people to collect it
and right to what degree can they seize property to pay the
half-שקל Shekel and so on. All right, so that's in question. But
anyway, that's how רש"י Rashi frames it. תוספות Tosafot doesn't like that.
תוספות Tosafot says that you—it is not a הלכה Halachah that it
works for you if you never pay. You actually do have to
pay. Okay, and if you don't pay, you actually the קרבנות Korbanot
are not brought for you. Not only that, תוספות Tosafot explains the
case about—is
that retroactively that I was never counted?
Yeah, I don't know. I mean what's the נפקא מינה, Nafkah Mina,
I mean up in שמים Shamayim I don't exactly know. But anyway,
but hold on, let me take—I just want to look at one
thing more in תוספות Tosafot for one
minute.
Okay, so תוספות Tosafos said, right, אלא עביד מצוות alla avud mitzvos
only means things that eventually are going to get paid. So then
if that's true, I actually did do a favor for Michael because,
you know, if I hadn't paid him, he would have had to
have paid, and if he didn't pay, he never would have got
credit for the קרבנות. korbanot. So תוספות Tosafos says, I don't know,
this to me seems to be a much more דחוק dachuk read
of the גמרא. Gemara. תוספות Tosafos says no, but what it means
אלא עביד alla avud is Michael sent his money in and then
the money was lost, so technically he's already exempt from his obligation
because before it got to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? The money was taken,
קרבנות korbanot were brought when it was on the way and then
it got lost and so on. So he's technically exempt and I
so feel, but he feels bad, yes technically I'm exempt but my
money never got there, this and that, don't worry about it, I'll
go ahead and I'll pay for you a second time. And that
that's the case in the משנה Mishnah where he actually has paid,
he is exempt, he has, it is working for him and I'm
just going ahead and paying yet again. So that's a very weak
read of the case. The גמרא Gemara makes it sound, the simple
read of the משנה Mishnah makes it sound like anytime I pay
his שקל shekel he's all, you know, that's okay. That's a standard
case of paying his שקל. shekel. So anyway, this is wait, wait,
so the גמרא's Gemara not a standard paying?
No, that's the way תוספות Tosafos reads the גמרא. Gemara.
If I really would pay your שקל, shekel, I really would have
given you benefit because you now, that would have made you a
part-owner of the קרבנות. korbanot. And that the case in the גמרא
Gemara is a case, one of these cases where you're technically exempt
and I'm choosing to pay anyway. It's not פשט. pshat. So basically
though, just to repeat, that was a little, that was a little
distracted. פשט pshat like רש"י Rashi is, certainly the פשט pshat is
anytime I pay Michael's שקל shekel it's okay, I didn't give him
any benefit. All right, and the reason why that רש"י Rashi basically
says is is because bottom line, he has a חלק cheilek in
the קרבנות korbanot anyway, and anything I do for him I'm helping
him with a מצוה, mitzvah, I haven't given him any really substantial
benefit. But it's going to get clear in a minute because if
you think about it even in the, even in the worst case
of the שקל, shekel, it's basically just a debt that he owes
הקדש. Hekdesh. So really we're going to have to figure out anyway
how to deal with the case about why I can pay off
his debt. And that's a real benefit. So if we can understand
why I can pay off his debt, we'll have a better understanding
of why I can pay off his שקל, shekel, yes.
Is the difference here between רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos when it
says in the משנה Mishnah המודר הנאה, hamudar hana'ah, is
does it mean a monetary הנאה hana'ah or does it mean an
emotional הנאה? hana'ah?
Well, yeah, I mean it does mean monetary. So that, I mean,
emotional is does not count. There, it has to be something more
concrete. רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos are not debating the definition of
הנאה. hana'ah. They're just debating why is it that the שקל shekel
case doesn't fall into that category? Is it really true that Michael
always has a חלק cheilek in the קרבנות?
korbanot? And they both believe הנאה hana'ah is monetary?
It basically is monetary, yeah.
So now, if you can cancel each other's jokes.
Right, right, now, so now to, okay. So anyway, it's a little
bit unclear, like I said, the simple sense of the גמרא Gemara
without sort of unpacking it further is: All right, Michael really would
have gotten off or wouldn't have had any real consequence of owing
his שקל shekel anyway so I didn't do him much of a
favor. Okay. Now we're going to get, again, the real question is
going to be paying off his debts, and that's also why it's
really relevant to us. Okay. אלא ומציל אבידתו נמי מצוה קעביד, ela
u-matzil avidato nami mitzvah k'avid,
I'm doing a מצוה, mitzvah, I'm not really doing it for Michael,
and what really needs to be added here also is is that
I'm really just giving him his own thing back. אלא פורע את
חובו בקמשתרש ליה, ela poreia es chovo ba'kamesh-taresh lei, I am, now
what's בקמשתרש ליה? ba'kamesh-taresh lei? רש"י Rashi says it means I'm, I'm
benefiting him, I'm, you know, I'm causing him profit, but also the
word seems to be like from the word שורש, shoresh, I'm like
in, you know, like my, like the benefit I gave him is
sort of like entrenched, you know, buried in his, like rooted down
in his property. I basically paid off his creditor and now he's
got, he's free from it and he actually has real concrete benefit,
right? He's free from that debt, he has like, you know, his
net worth has gone up as a result, right? You have that
much less on your debits column.
So isn't that, didn't he really get something? So אמר רב אושעיא
הא מני חנן היא, amar Rav Oshaya ha-mani Chanan hi, this is
חנן, Chanan, דאמר איבד את מעותיו, de-amar ibid es ma'osav,
he wasted his money. So what does wasted his money, how are
these two ideas related? And bottom line is here's what it, here's
how it worked out between רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafos, here's what
they say. I go ahead and I pay off these, Michael's creditor
or I pay off the woman who essentially is the husband's creditor
when the husband is away and she needs her food. Okay. Is
it considered, but let's take the case of paying off Michael's creditor.
Is it considered like I directly gave Michael something, right? Because now
he has less debt on his property or whatever and his property
value has increased etc.? Or is it considered to be, so he
directly got something from me? Or no? He didn't get something from
me, the creditor got something from me and indirectly... he got, like
that phrase תוספות Tosafos used before, that מבריח ארי מנכסי חבירו, mavirach
ari minichsei chaveiro, right?
Indirectly what he got was that somebody is now not making demand,
somebody is not whatever, is not going to take away his property.
But again, because it's the non-taking away, it's not the increased value,
and because the money didn't go to Michael, the money went to
Michael's creditor, right, we can actually say I didn't directly give Michael
anything. Okay, I gave Michael's creditor something, as a result as a
גרמא grama indirectly, it means that somebody is now not going to
be demanding that debt. Interesting. Like being freed from the lien, being
freed from having that debt outstanding, again is removing something bad, but
I actually have not directly contributed some value to you or to
your property. And if that's what חנן Chanan says, this is why
I'm not entitled to get paid when I do it for the
wife, then that shows that that's how חנן Chanan is conceptually thinking
about it. I did not directly do anything for the husband, and
therefore I cannot demand, I didn't increase his value, I didn't do
him a service, it's not seen as doing a service for the
husband, right? And therefore if that's true in terms of why I
can't collect money when I pay his wife, that's also why I
did not do anything wrong when I pay off Michael's creditor.
So but if you just lend me money, you know I have
to give you back the same amount of money, it hasn't increased,
but you still viewed as doing me service so that you wouldn't
be able to do...
One more time?
So let's say you just lend me money. Yeah. So I have
to give you back the money.
Right, so if I waive that debt...
No, let's not waive that debt. Let's say you just lend me,
you know, okay I, you swear...
Can I lend you money if, if, if you're מודר הנאה modar
hana'ah from me? Yeah, that's interesting.
Yeah, I'm sure that's discussed, I don't remember it offhand. Okay, but
let's take a look at the first line of תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות
Tosafos says הא מני חנן היא דאמר אבן מעסף הוא והן שאינו
יכול עתה לטובעו ממנו אף על פי שמכל מקום מהנהו שאין צריך
לשלם חובו.
Ha mani Chanan hi de'amar Eben Moasaf ho vehen she'eino yachol ata
letov'o mimenu af
al pi shemickol makom mehanehu she'ein tzarich leshalem chovo. I benefited you,
you don't have to pay your
debt, but משום הכי לא מיתסר שאינו אלא גרמא בעלמא שעל ידי
שפורע זה לבעל חובו נסתלק. mishum hachi lo mityasar she'eino ela grama
be'alma she'al yedei sheporeh zeh leba'al chovo nistack. Because I paid off
your creditor, you're now free. אף על פי Af al pi the
ודמי להא דתנן המודר הנאה udami leha detnan hamodar hana'ah etc. Okay,
and so we'll read the other example, because that's another good example.
הא דתנן באין ביניהם המודר המודר הנאה מחבירו ואין לו מה יאכל.
Ha detnan bein beineihem hamodar hamodar hana'ah mechaiveiro ve'ein lo mah yochal.
Here, Michael is starving and I don't know what to do for
him. What can I do? ילך אצל חנווני הרגיל אצלו. Yelech eitzel
chanvani haragil etzlo. I go to, right, we had this before, I
go to a storekeeper, I say, you know, נעבך nebach Michael doesn't
have any food to eat, he's starving, if only somebody would choose
to pay him, would choose to provide him food, I'm sure that
person would be reimbursed. Okay, ויטול הוא שם מתנה דאף על גב
דעל ידו משתלמי מזוני.
Veyitol hu sham matanah
de'af al gav de'al yado mishtalmei mizonei. Even though in that case
as a result of my actions, Michael is now getting some real
food sent to his house, הואיל ולא עביד אלא גרמא בעלמא. ho'il
velo avid ela grama be'alma. I was only acting indirectly and external
to Michael. Okay, that's okay. ודלא דמי לעושה לו מלאכה. Vedela dami
le'oseh lo melachah. That would be, it's not like I went and
I mowed Michael's lawn. דאסור אף על גב דלא מצי תביא ליה
מיניה. De'asur af al gav de'lo matzi tavei lei minei. Even though
I couldn't make Michael pay me for mowing his lawn.
דהתם מדידי לדידיה קא מיתהני. Dehatam mididi ledidei ka mitahni. Because then
he directly got something from me. If I went and I mowed
his lawn, even if there is no way I could tell him
pay me twenty bucks, right, so there's no, but nevertheless he directly
got some benefit from me. From me to him went now the
improvement of his lawn. So that is some direct benefit. But here,
from me went money to the storekeeper, or from me went money
to the creditor. And then that creditor, that storekeeper, decided, went ahead
and they gave Michael food, or they gave, or they, you know,
Michael no longer has the debt to them. So that's indirect. And
it's the indirectness as that makes us that, you know, and the
fact also that it didn't result in any increased... well, in the
storekeeper case, it actually did result in increased value, he actually got
food. But in the debt case, it didn't result in any direct
increased value, it just went from removing a debt, but not an
actual increase. So that what is what allows me to say that,
like why חנן Chanan says I don't owe the guy anymore, because
he didn't do anything for me directly. But that's why in the
flip case, I can do it for Michael because it's not like
I'm giving him anything. Yes.
I think I'm thinking off-track because it seems to me that if
you're paying a debtor a lot, you're doing more for Michael than
mowing his lawn.
I know. So in practical terms, that's why, no, you're not off.
I mean, in practical, real-world terms, I'd much rather you pay off,
like I said, my student debts or my mortgage than I would
that you mowed my lawn, right? But in, but anyway, but in
what do you call it, I mean, in the technical framing of
did I directly receive a benefit, not how much, you know, how
much really am I now in a better position, but whether it's
seen as directly I got something from you or indirectly, you know,
it's a, yeah...
But it seems to me it is very direct. You go to
sleep at night not worrying. I know.
No, your benefit is, your benefit is huge, but the question is
not how much did you benefit, but how much is it seen
as you got something from that person. It's a technical point. No,
you're right, intuitively it, it seems you did get a lot. But
that's the, that's the... Let's take a look at the מהרש"א Maharsha
first.
If you put the money in my bank account then I could
pay...
Exactly, exactly. Okay. So,
alright. There was a story like that. I'm trying to remember who
it was said about. I don't remember if it was about Donald
Trump or somebody else. I remember the story was going around about
ten years ago that somebody was like,
I think it was about Donald Trump. Anyway, somebody was like saw
somebody on the side of the street having problems, whatever, he got
out, he helped him change his tire. Anyway, it turned out that
it was like, you know,
Donald Trump or something, I think. Anyway, so he said like, you
know, what can I do for you? Let me
go, I really want to show you my gratitude. He says, no,
no, no, don't do anything. So he kept on insisting, says fine,
you know what? It's ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, send my wife some
flowers, like here's my address. Anyway, so he goes home and then
he finds out that like his whole mortgage had been paid off.
There's a discussion שקלים Shekalim about paying someone's half shekel contribution.
Yeah, so that's what this is, paying the half shekel. Okay, let's
go on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ורבא אמר צדת
צדת דרבי אושעיה V'Rava amar tzadat tzadat d'Rav Oshaya says it's חנן,
Hanan, so you didn't really do anything for him, at least in
a technical sense. Okay, ורבא אמר, Rava amar, Rava says, אפילו תימא
רבנן, afilu tema Rabbanan, it could even be the Rabbis meaning the
בני כהנים גדולים. Bnei Kohanim Gedolim. Now all of a sudden they
became the Rabbis. Anyway, so it's who said that actually you would
owe the person something if they paid off your wife's and it
actually is doing something for you. הכא במאי עסקינן שלוה על מנת
שלא לפרוע. hacha b'mai askinan she-lava al menat she-lo lifroa.
The case would be in that when are you out to pay
off his debt when Michael had some very special arrangements with his
creditors? He borrowed the money on condition that he wouldn't have to
pay them back.
So Rava says it doesn't mean he'd never
have to pay them back, but it basically means they could never
demand it in court, he would always be his option, he could
always choose when to pay them back, they can never demand him
to pay. So in that type of a case where it's indefinite
when he ever has to pay them back, it's like it's only
theoretically on my debt column, because a debt that nobody can ever
demand its payment of, even though in theory I owe the money,
is not really a debt on my debt column, and therefore you
didn't really do me much of a favor. So the גמרא Gemara
says בשלמא רבא לא אמר כרבי אושעיה, B'shlama Rava lo amar k'Rav
Oshaya, I get why Rava didn't say like רבי אושעיה Rav Oshaya
who made it like חנן. Hanan.
דמוקים לה כרבנן, d'mukim leh k'Rabbanan, he'd rather have it go like
the Rabbis, not like the position of חנן, Hanan, although it is
interesting because the sense one gets in the משנה Mishnah is that
we go like חנן, Hanan, right, although he's a דעת יחיד da'at
yachid here? I mean, I don't know how much is it a
דעת יחיד da'at yachid against בני כהנים גדולים, Bnei Kohanim Gedolim, that's
also anyway. All right, but anyway, he'd rather have them go like
the majority position. אלא אושעיה מאי טעמא לא אמר כרבא? Ella Oshaya
mai ta'ama lo amar k'Rava? Why didn't he say like Rava to
make it this special case of a debt you didn't have to
pay off? So, because anyway it certainly doesn't sound that way. אמר
לך רבי אושעיה, Amar lach Rav Oshaya, Rav Oshaya will tell you
נהי דהנאה לית ליה כיסופא מי לית ליה? nehi d'hana layt leh
kissufa mi layt leh? Even if technically I didn't benefit Michael because
nobody would have ever demanded the debt to be
paid, are you telling me Michael wouldn't be embarrassed? Right, if he
would run into his creditors, even if they could never make him
come to court, they would still say, you know נו, nu, like
you know, you still haven't paid it off, oh yeah whatever, you
can't take me, I know I can't take you to court, but
you have it to pay it. So therefore, because I would have
saved him from that embarrassment, it's also actually giving him some real
benefit. התם נמי איכא הנאה והיא הנאה דמכסיף מיניה. Hatam nami ika
hana v'hi hana d'michasaf mineh. That benefit that I'm preventing him from
being embarrassed, that actually would be giving him real benefit. I know
that is not monetary, which is that important question about how exactly
you know do you measure a type of a benefit that is,
right, that is not monetary, which is correct. So that does raise
important questions about נדרים, Nedarim, but anyway, and also it's a very
weak אוקימתא ukimta of the whole case, that it's that very special
scenario. But what's more important for us is appreciating that it helps
us understand
חנן's Hanan approach, which is that even though, yes, the person got
an extreme amount of benefit, he now is free from having to
pay back his wife or to pay back his creditors and so
on, in a technical sense is seen as coming only indirectly. There's
two points again: one is indirect, and the other is it did
not result in an increased value of the property, and that's what
sort of allows us to be saying this. Okay. That idea that
like, even if you don't actually owe it, you're still going to
be
embarrassed, like, sometimes
Rabbi Love, who's at the ישיבה, Yeshiva, tells the story that he
bumped in once on the street to a, I forget who it
was, I think it was Sussman or whatever, one of anyway one
of his teachers from graduate school in Jewish studies, whatever, like twenty
years later, and he says, don't you still owe me a paper?
And he says, yes, he said, how did you remember? He says,
everybody still owes me papers.
Yes, and
I owe New York Telephone one cent on an unpaid bill from
back when I was
in college.
There you go.
All
right,
let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah. All right. Excuse
me one second. Yeah.
I'm very disturbed by the moral issues here about you take out
you take money from someone as the loan and you really don't
have any sense of obligation.
No, no, that was the, that was the. Exactly. Exactly. You
can imagine a case like that. Okay. All right, next משנה Mishna
*mishna*. אלמנה משיבה *Almonah mishiva*.
Okay, so that's actually the two statements that חנן Chanan *Chanan* said.
Now אדמון Admon. *Admon* said seven statements and now we're going to
go through them.
לא פסקנא בהדיא *La paskanah behadya*.
We didn't explicitly פסקן *pasken*. מי שמת והניח בנים ובנות *Mi shemes
vehiniach banim uvanos*. Somebody died and left over sons and daughters. Okay,
and remember the daughters have a right to be supported by the
estate, the sons inherit everything. בזמן שהנכסים מרובים *Bizman shehanechasim merubim*, if
there's a large estate, הבנים יירשו *habanim yirashu*, the sons inherit, והבנות
יזונו *vehabanos yizonu*, and the daughters are fed. ובנכסים מועטים *Uvnechasim muatim*,
if there's a small amount of the estate and so small that
there's not even enough money to provide for the food for both
the sons and the daughters, okay, let alone that there'll be left
over afterwards. So in that case, הבנות יזונו והבנים יחזרו על הפתחים
*habanos yizonu vehabanim yechaizeru al hapesachim*.
So the, we have to choose, we would have to use the
money to provide for the food for the daughters and if the
sons go hungry and they have to go begging, that's what the
sons have to do. אדמון אומר Admon Omer *Admon omer*, אדמון Admon
*Admon* says, בשביל שאני זכר הפסדתי *bishvil she'ani zachar hifsadeti*, just because
I'm a male I lose out? You know it's the patriarchy, I'm
never supposed to lose out my privilege. So
right, so we should all equally be supported, boys and girls. אמר
רבן גמליאל Amar Rabban Gamliel רואה אני את דברי אדמון Ro'eh Ani
Es Divrei Admon, *Amar Rabban Gamliel ro'eh ani es divrei
Admon*, I see the position of אדמון Admon *Admon*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, מאי קאמר *mai ka'amar*, why does
he think that just because he's a male he shouldn't lose out?
אמר אביי הכי קאמר *Amar Abaye hachi ka'amar*, בשביל שאני זכר וראוי
לעסוק בתורה הפסדתי *bishvil she'ani zachar vera'ui la'asok baTorah hifsadeti*? You know,
if you have to pay for somebody's food bill it should be
the people that are doing more important things in society, the people
that are learning תורה *Torah*. So it should, so why should I,
you know, I get fed last? So אמר ליה רבא *amar lei
Rava*, I don't get it. מאן דעסיק בתורה הוא דירית מאן דלא
עסיק בתורה לא ירית *Man de'asik beTorah hu deyaris man dela asik
beTorah lo yaris*? Somebody that learns תורה *Torah* gets an inheritance and
somebody that does not does not? That's not very nice that you're
saying that you know men are better than women, like talking about
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s you know that are very clear about how
they, people try to give these apologetics for the שלא עשני אשה
*shelo asani isha* ברכה *bracha*. I mean, you know, גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
had very clear views about that. Anyway, so he says look, you
know, that's all very nice that you know we might do something
that we see as religiously or socially more important, society more important,
but that's not what we're discussing. We're discussing you know your sort
of monetary rights and why is that relevant to a question of
who should have more rights to the property? So therefore, if you
want to make that argument, here's the argument. אלא אמר רבא הכי
קאמר *Ella amar Rava hachi ka'amar*, בשביל שאני זכר וראוי לירש בנכסים
מרובים *bishvil she'ani zachar vera'ui liyarash benechasim merubim*, look as a male
I fundamentally have more rights to the estate. I'm entitled to get
a, to actually be an heir to the estate and the girls
don't have, if there was a large estate, a million dollar estate,
I would be the primary person to benefit from it. I have
the more rights here. הפסדתי בנכסים מועטים *Hifsadeti benechasim muatim*? So when
it's a small estate they should have a privilege over me and
we should feed them before we feed me? Okay, so that, anyway,
it's quite fascinating what this reveals right about attitudes towards you know
men and women and so on and רבא *Rava*'s in disagreement with
that basic perspective, just saying it's not really relevant to this you
know financial to this financial issue. Now by the way though, the
question is what do you mean בשביל שאני זכר הפסדתי *bishvil she'ani
zachar hifsadeti*? And you know do we wind up פסקן *paskening* that
way? If you take a look at תוספות *Tosfos*, תוספות *Tosfos* says
the following. He says אף על גב
דקדמה לקמן *af al gav dekadma lekaman*, תוספות *Tosfos* in the אדמון
אומר Admon omer, *Admon omer*, דקדמה לקמן *dekadma lekaman*, כל מקום שאמר
רבן גמליאל רואה אני את דברי אדמון הלכה כמותו *kol makom she'amar
Rabban Gamliel ro'eh ani es divrei Admon halacha kemoso*, and therefore when
רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* says it looks like אדמון *Admon* is right
or אדמון *Admon*'s position makes sense, it sounds like we should rule
that way and say that we would not privilege the girls over
the boys in a small estate. מיהו פסקא פרכא דאשכחן לקמן *Mihu
piska parcha de'ashchechan lekaman* etc. מכל מקום אומר רבינו תם *mikol makom
omer Rabbeinu Tam* דלא וסוגיין דגמרא דלא כוותיה בהא *delo vesugyan deGemara
dela kevasye beha*, we don't rule that way in this case. דסוגיין
דגמרא דלא כוותיה *Desugyan deGemara dela kevasye*, if you remember from earlier
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*s, we always said that in a small estate the
girls do get a privilege over the boys. The girls get supported.
בפרק נערה *Beperek Na'arah*, אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן עשו אלמנה
אצל בת כבת אצל אחין בנכסים מועטים *amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi
Yochanan asu almonah eitzel bas kebas eitzel achin benechasim muatim* etc etc.
And then he says I'm like five lines from the bottom after
the after parenthesis, ואומר רבינו תם דהיינו טעמא *ve'omer Rabbeinu Tam dehainu
ta'ama*, this is why we rule not like אדמון *Admon* even though
רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* says we go like, right, he makes sense,
דאדמון לאו פליגי אמילתא דחכמים עבדו *de'Admon lav peligi amilsa dechachamim avdu*,
אדמון *Admon* isn't really arguing about the הלכה *halacha*. He concedes: yes,
I know that that's the הלכה *halacha* that the girls get supported
before the boys. אלא מתמה בעלמא *ella misma be'alma*, he's just saying
I know it's the הלכה *halacha* but it doesn't make any sense.
He's just like voicing outrage. Okay, but he's not actually arguing הלכה
*halachically*. ורבן גמליאל נמי Nami, דאמר מהאי לאו רואה אני את דברי
אדמון *veRabban Gamliel nami de'amar mehai lav ro'eh ani es divrei Admon*,
לאו משום פסק דין *lav mishum psak din*, he's not saying we
rule like אדמון *Admon*, אלא משום שיש בו כדי לתמוה *ella mishum
sheyesh bo kedei litmo'ah*. Yeah, I share his sense of outrage. Okay,
so it's quite interesting right that he רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* sided
with him, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* later said when רבן גמליאל *Rabban
Gamliel* sides with אדמון *Admon* we go that way, but here it's
very clear from other גמרא Gemara *Gemara*s that the girls get supported,
not the boys, and that leads תוספות *Tosfos* to reinterpret that אדמון
*Admon* isn't really debating הלכה *halachically*, he's just voicing a sort of
outrage. sense of outrage that נעבעך once a man should actually lose
out in the patriarchy. Yes.
Wait, why do the girls get more advantage in the נכסים מועטים?
nechasim muatim?
Well, there's two ways of understanding it. One is to understand as
a text you know sort of in the legal sense that they
have a debt and the boy so it's like any other creditor
that has a debt on the estate that they're entitled to collect
their debt before the heirs get their inheritance, right? So that's just
one simple way. And the other way is actually because of to
protect the girls from the you know it's much harder for her
to force girls to go out and to go to go out
begging than it is to demand that of the boy. Okay, let's
take a look at the next משנה Mishnah. הטוען את חברו כדי
שמן. Hatoyen Es Chaveiro Kadei Shemen.
So
now this has nothing to do with מסכת כתובות Masechet Ketubot but
it's a teaching of אדמון. Somebody says to his friend, you owe
me jugs of oil, 100 jugs of oil. והודה בקנקנים Vehodeh Bekankanim
and he says you know what I owe you the jugs, I
don't owe you the oil. Okay. So this is a question about
מודה במקצת. Modeh Bemiktzas. Everybody knows if I say you owe me
$100 and you concede yes I owe you $20 but not 100,
you have to take a שבועה. Shvua. Now what if you concede
something I did not ask you about? I said you owed me
100 bushels of wheat and you said no I owe you 100
bushels of barley. So that's טענו חיטין Tanu Chitin I demanded wheat
והודה לו בשעורין Vehodeh Lo Besorim and you conceded barley. And since
you conceded something that I did not ask for, that's not a
מודה במקצת Modeh Bemiktzas even though it is
a even though it's of a lesser value than I was asking.
So here when I say you owed me 100 jugs of oil,
included in the 100 jugs of oil are the jugs and you've
conceded to the jugs. So are you a
מודה במקצת? Modeh Bemiktzas? Okay. So אדמון אומר הוא והודה במקצת הטענה,
Hu Vehodeh Bemiktzas Hatana, ישבע, Yishava, you conceded to the jugs so
you have to take
an oath. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim Omrim אין הודאת מקצת ממין הטענה, Ein
Hoda'as Miktzas Mimin Hatana, you are not really conceding to part of
the of the of the claim. אמר רבן גמליאל רואה אני את
דברי אדמון, you know what Admon says makes sense. So it sounds
like what they're debating is the חכמים Chachamim say that even though
when you say 100 jugs, obviously you mean the you know jugs
itself are included but that's really not what you care about and
that's really not what you're demanding. And if the guy basically agreed
to return you that amount of oil in a barrel without the
jugs, presumably you'd be okay with it. So therefore you're not really
demanding the jugs. That seems to be the debate. Let's take a
look at what the
גמרא Gemara, says. שמע מינה לרבנן, Shma Mina Lerabbanan, so it sounds
from the rabbis who say that you are exempt that טענו חיטין
ושעורין והודה בשעורין פטור.
Tanu Chitin Useorim Vehodeh Beseorim
Patur. So let's say I I sort of made it like that
the reason the rabbis said you're exempt is because you really don't
care about the jugs. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't understand it that
way. It sounds like, let's say I said you owe me 100
bushels of wheat and 100 bushels of barley and you conceded to
the to the barley, okay, so are you being מודה במקצת? Modeh
Bemiktzas? Because I made a claim of A and B and you
conceded to the B part of it. Are you not being מודה
במקצת Modeh Bemiktzas because we look at those as two separate claims?
Because they're two separate objects, there's one claim of A and one
claim of B. You fully conceded to the claim of B and
you fully rejected the claim of A. Right, does do people see
that? You look at it as one claim to which you admit
half or two separate claims, one you fully admitted to and one
you fully rejected. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara thinks that that's why
the rabbis say you're exempt because when I say 100 jugs, that's
two claims, 100 units of oil and 100 jugs. And you've conceded
to the jugs and rejected the oil. So that's two separate claims
and you've completely rejected one. That's how it understands why the rabbis
say you're exempt. שמע מינה לרבנן, Shma Mina Lerabbanan, we see for
the rabbis, טענו חיטין ושעורין והודה בשעורין פטור. Tanu Chitin Useorim Vehodeh
Beseorim Patur. Okay and that's why you're exempt because you completely rejected
the oil part of the claim. So לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרב נחמן
אמר שמואל. Lima Tevei Tyuvta Derav Nachman Amar Shmuel. This should be
a contradiction to Rav Nachman Amar Shmuel. דאמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל,
Da'amar Rav Nachman Amar Shmuel, טענו חיטין ושעורין, Tanu Chitin Useorim, if
you claimed wheat and barley, והודה באחד מהן, Vehodeh Beachad Mehen, and
you conceded one of them, חייב. Chayav. You're חייב, Chayav, we look
at that as one claim, not as two
claims. So if so if that's true that we would normally look
at that as one claim, why shouldn't אדמון be right? So אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav בטוענו מידה. Beto'ano
Midah. Okay. No, no, no, because here the case is, you're right.
Normally that would be and you would be right. But here the
difference is that you're not saying you owe me 100 jugs of
oil, you're saying you owe me 100 jugs worth of oil. You
never actually made the claim for the jugs at all, just for
that quantity. And that's why you're exempt because you're not actually claiming
the jugs. So the גמרא Gemara says wait minute, אי הכי מאי
טעמא דאדמון? Ei hachi mai tama deAdmon? So then what's Admon's reasoning
if you're not if you're not talking about the jugs at all?
אלא אמר רבא דכולי עלמא היכא דאמר ליה Ella Amar Rava Dechulei
Alma Heicha De'amar Lei מלא עשרה כדי שמן יש לי בבורך. Melei
Asara Kadei Shemen Yesh Li Bevorcha. Everybody says that if you said
the fill
of ten jugs of wine I have in your you know in
your pit so clearly the jugs are not what's being demanded just
that
quantity.
So שמן קא טעין
וקנקנים לא
קא טעין.
Shamen Ka Ta'ein Vekankanim
Lo Ka Ta'ein.
If you however you
said עשרה כדי שמן מלאין יש לי אצלך, Asarah kadei shemen melei'in
yesh li etzkha, I have ten jugs filled with oil, so clearly
you're interested in both: the jugs and the oil that's in it.
So in that case שמן וקנקנים קטעין ליה, Shemen ve-kankanin katein lei,
you'd be asking for both, and everybody would agree that you would
be חייב, chayav, that conceding even one of those two claims is
considered מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzat. We're assuming now like רב נחמן אמר
שמואל Rav Nachman amar Shmuel that a claim of two separate objects
gets wrapped up as one claim. So if you were clearly asking
for both, ten jugs filled with oil, so you're asking for the
jugs and the oil, then a concession of the jugs is a
מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzat. So what's the debate? So כי פליגי, ki
pligi, when they are debating היכא דאמר ליה heicha de-amar lei עשרה
כדי שמן יש לי אצלך. asarah kadei shemen yesh li etzkha.
You don't say the fill of ten jugs, which focuses only on
the oil. You don't say ten jugs filled with oil, which focuses
on both. You just say "ten jugs of oil". So what, when
you say "ten jugs of oil", are you really talking about the
jugs at all? That's the debate. Okay. Which I think is what
we would have intuitively understood what the debate was about. כדי שמן
יש לי אצלך. kadei shemen yesh li etzkha. חנן אומר Chanan omer
יש בלשון הזה לשון קנקנים. yesh ba-lashon hazeh lashon kankanin. When you
say ten jugs of oil, you're also you also want the jugs.
Okay. ורבנן
סברי Ve-rabbanan savri אין בלשון הזה לשון קנקנים. ein ba-lashon hazeh lashon
kankanin. No, you really just care about the oil. Okay. So everybody
agrees that if you clearly asked for jugs and oil and they
conceded jugs, that would be מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzat. The question is
when you say ten jugs of oil, how much are you really
talking about jugs altogether? Okay. Fine. So that seems like a very
good explanation of the debate. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אלא טעמא דאין בלשון הזה לשון קנקנים. Ela ta'ama de-ein ba-lashon
hazeh lashon kankanin. So the reason, so now what the debate is
about whether you're actually referring to jugs at all. הא יש בלשון
הזה לשון קנקנים, Ha yesh ba-lashon hazeh lashon kankanin, if implicitly, if
you were or whatever what the suggestion is that if you were
explicitly mentioning the jugs, you said ten jugs filled with oil, חייב,
chayav, everybody would agree you'd be חייב. chayav. Right? So everybody agrees
that when you say jugs and oil and you concede one of
them that it's a מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzat. The only issue is
whether you are actually referring to the jugs at all. So if
that's true, לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרבי חייא בר אבא, leima tehevei tiyuvta
de-Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, that should contradict רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba that says the opposite of רב נחמן אמר שמואל.
Rav Nachman amar Shmuel. דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא De-amar Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba טענו חיטין ושעורין, ta'ano chitin u-se'orin, if you demanded wheat
and barley, והודה לו באחד מהן ve-hoda lo be-echad mehen and you
conceded one of them, פטור, patur, you're exempt. So it's funny, like
what we did is first we, you know, we sort of started
with one and then we ended with the other. But now we're
getting to a point where we think that this is פשט pshat
in the משנה. Mishnah We think פשט pshat in the משנה Mishnah
is that if you explicitly said jugs and oil and you conceded
jugs, you'd be a מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzat. And that the debate
of the משנה Mishnah is when you say "ten jugs of oil",
how much is it that you really are including and addressing the
jugs themselves? Okay. But that assumes that in principle if you were
explicitly addressing the jugs and you conceded it, that would be considered
מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzat. What do you do about the opinion out
there that that's not מודה במקצת? modeh be-miktzat? If you say jugs
and oil, those are two separate claims, not one claim. So how
would you therefore explain the משנה according to that? So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. אמר רב שימי בר אשי amar Rav Shimi
bar Ashi נעשה כמי שטענו רמון בקליפתה. na'aseh ke-mi she-ta'ano rimon bi-kelipata.
Even if I say wheat and barley, that gets considered to be
two claims and not a מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzat. If I basically
say: you owe me ten pomegranates, and I say: no, I only
owe you the rinds of the ten pomegranates, not the actual pomegranates
themselves. Okay. Everybody would agree that that is really considered one claim.
Okay. Because the pomegranate with its rinds, even though you can theoretically
break them up into two separate objects, that's really all considered to
be one claim. Okay. Not two separate objects that are being claimed
together that we separate. So when I say "jugs of oil", even
if I said wheat and barley that would be essentially two claims,
jugs of oil is seen as one claim. The jug, the container
of the oil, is one thing and it's all one big claim
and you've conceded the part of the claim. Which makes a lot
of sense and maybe that's actually the debate of חנן and the
חכמים, Chachamim, whether you conceptualize jugs of oil, not whether I'm addressing
the jugs we can all concede that I am explicitly addressing the
jugs but whether we conceptualize that as two claims or as one
claim. Yes.
So why the attempt to learn it out from the wheat and
barley? The analogy would be baskets of wheat and baskets of or
baskets of barley.
Well, the debate was right, the point was this debate was about
a clear case of two completely unrelated
separate objects, but that are being said in the same sentence. Do
we conceptualize that as one or as two? What then has to
be analyzed is what do you do when those two objects are
more closely related?
And that's why the analogy doesn't hold. The true analogy would be
baskets of wheat.
Right. Right. But the גמרא, Gemara you know, wanted to argue from
something that you would intuitively agree to. You intuitively would agree that
the Right. Well, that’s what the גמרא’s Gemara now going to say
back. So let’s look at the גמרא’s Gemara response. Right, let’s look
at the גמרא’s Gemara response. So the גמרא’s Gemara response is exactly
this: you want to bring from an obvious case that might be
obvious but it might not be so relevant. So the גמרא Gemara
says מתקיף לה רבינא Matkif lah Ravina or Ravina asked them this,
רימון בלא קליפתו לא מינטר. Rimon belo klipato lo mintar.
A pomegranate without its shell won’t be protected. Of course that’s one
indivisible object or clearly that’s one
claim. Okay, שמן מינטר בלא קנקנים. Shemen mintar belo kankanin. You can
have oil without the jugs. You can protect them in other things.
You put them in a well, you can put them in a
barrel, you put them in all other things. They’re not tightly connected
to the jugs that they were part of. So what he’s basically
saying is that, but you could have said maybe that’s exactly the
debate of אדמון והחכמים. Admon ve-hachachamim. How much is something and its
container, even though it’s not a necessary container but it happens to
be the container, how much is that conceptualized as one claim or
as two claims? But the גמרא wants to say that if normally
you think wheat and barley are two claims, then you should treat
oil and the jugs as two claims as well. Yes.
Isn’t it also whether it’s a measurement or a physical object? The
word jug?
Yes, so we said before, if you’re clearly dealing with a measurement,
you say ten measures, the measure of ten jugs, then of course
it’s taken for granted. Right, yeah. But if you’re saying here they’re
trying to say that it’s not a question of what you meant.
Even if you explicitly say ten jugs filled with oil. So you’re
explicitly clear that you mean both. Do we package that as one
claim or as two claims? So you could say that’s exactly the
debate of אדמון והחכמים. Admon ve-hachachamim. But the גמרא’s saying is that
if normally you treat wheat and barley as two claims, then because
the jugs and the oil are not intrinsically connected intertwined, then we
could also be treating that as two separate claims. So let’s take
a look now as the גמרא continues. So if that’s true, why
isn’t this two claims and why wouldn’t everybody say you’d be exempt?
So the גמרא says like this, אלא
הכא במאי עסקינן. Ella hacha bemai askinan. What are we talking about?
דאמר ליה, De-amar leh, עשרה כדי שמן יש לי אצלך. Asarah kadei
shemen yesh li etzlecha. He says, “I have ten jugs of oil,”
which we now say means jugs and oil. And that’s clear and
that’s two separate claims. Okay. והאמר ליה Ve-ha-amar leh and he said
back to him אידך, Idach, שמן לא היו דברים מעולם. Shemen lo
hayu devarim me-olam. As far as the oil, I never owed any
oil. קנקנים, Kankanin, as far as the jugs, נמי, חמישה אית לך
וחמישה לית לך. Chamishah it lach ve-chamishah leit lach. I only owe
you five jugs, not the other five. Okay, so now what’s the
debate? This is just going to let us get back to what
we said before, that the debate is how to interpret the language.
אדמון אומר, יש בלשון הזה לשון קנקנים. Yesh bi-leshon zeh leshon kankanin.
When I say you owe me ten jugs of oil, that means
I’m not only asking for the oil, I’m also asking for the
jug. And since I’m asking for the jugs, and you conceded half
of the claim of the jugs, you’re a מודה במקצת Modeh be-miktzat
because you admitted to five jugs.
ומיגו דקמשתבע אקנקנים, U-migo de-kamishtava a-kankanin, since you have to take an
oath about the other five jugs because I was asking for the
jugs and you did concede part of that claim, משתבע נמי אשמן,
Mishtava nami a-shemen, so you also have to take an oath on
the oil because that’s a גלגול שבועה. Gilgul shevuah. Once I can
get you to take an oath about one thing, I can get
you to take an oath about the other. על ידי גלגול, Al
yedei gilgul, by rolling the שבועה shevuah to the other thing. ורבנן
סברי, Ve-rabbanan savri, the Rabbis hold, אין בלשון הזה לשון קנקנים. Ein
bi-leshon zeh leshon kankanin. No, when you say ten jugs of oil,
you’re really only asking about the oil, not about the jugs. מה
שטענו לא הודה לו ומה שהודה לו לא טענו. Mah she-te-ano lo
hodeh lo u-mah she-hodeh lo lo te-ano. So you conceded to the
jugs, but you were never being asked about the jugs, and therefore
you never have to make a שבועה. shevuah. So basically, just to
step back and review what we have. Assuming that when I claim
two separate things, we see that as one claim and just conceding
to one of them, you’re going to be חייב שבועה. Chayav shevuah.
The debate is when I say ten jugs of oil and you
concede to the jugs, was I really asking you about the jugs?
אדמון says that I was asking you about the jugs and therefore
you take a שבועה, shevuah, and the חכמים Chachamim say I wasn’t
and you don’t. That’s assuming that when I ask you for two
things, that’s considered to be one claim. And then the only question
is: was I really asking about the jugs? The other way of
approaching it, I would say the better way of approaching it according
to the other opinion which the גמרא ignored, is that if I’m
asking you for two things it’s normally considered two claims. And here
it’s clear that I am asking you for two things. But maybe
the debate is to what degree you conceptualize jugs and oil as
two separate things or as one thing? That could have been one
way of saying it. Do you put it in the רימון Rimon
and the shell category, or do you put it in the wheat
and the barley category? That could have been exactly the debate of
אדמון והחכמים. Admon ve-hachachamim. When you say oil and jugs, are you
seeing that as one claim or as two claims? But anyway, the
גמרא winds up making it a much more complicated issue, that clearly
I would separate it as two claims and really what we're really
just debating is when you conceded half of the claim of the
jugs, and was I really ever even asking about the jugs at
all or not? When I say jugs of oil, am I really
just asking about the oil or am I also asking about the
jugs?
Okay, so we will end with that and more
tomorrow.